I'm an Iranian-American Muslim female,
أنا امرأة إيرانية أمريكية مسلمة،
like all of you.
مثل كل واحد فيكم.
And I'm also a social justice comedian,
وأنا أيضاً فنانة كوميديا العدالة الإجتماعية،
something that I insist is an actual job.
وهو الشيء الذي أصرُ على أنه عمل فعلي.
To explain what that is, let me tell you how I got here.
لتوضيح معنى ذلك، اسمحوا لي أن أخبركم كيف وصلتُ إلى هنا.
I've performed all over the country.
أنا أمثلُ في جميع أنحاء البلاد.
And let me tell you, America is majestic, right?
وإسمحوا لي أن أخبركم أن أمريكا عريقة، أليس كذلك؟
It's got breathtaking nature,
حصلت على طبيعتها المهيبة،
waffle houses
مطاعم بسكويت الوفل
and diabetes as far as the eye can see.
ومرض السكري على مد البصر.
It is really something.
إنه حقاً شيء ما.
Now, the American population can be broken up
حالياً، يمكنُ تقسيم سكان أمريكا
into three main categories:
إلى ثلاث فئات رئيسية:
there's mostly wonderful people,
في الغالب هناك أناس رائعون،
haters
والحاقدون
and Florida.
وفلوريدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Besides Florida, the most troubling category here are the Haters.
بالإضافة إلى فلوريدا، أكثر فئة إثارة للقلق هنا هي الحاقدون.
They are a minority,
إنهم أقلية،
but they overcompensate by being extra loud.
لكنهم يعوضوِّن عن مشاكلهم بكونهم أكثر حدّة.
They have the Napoleon complex of demographics,
لديهم عقدة نابليون بشأن التركيبة السكانية،
and yes, some of the men do wear heels.
ونعم، يرتدي بعض الرجال الكعب العالي.
As a social justice comedian,
وكممثلة كوميديا العدالة الإجتماعية،
it's my goal to convert these haters,
هدفي هو تغيير هؤلاء الحاقدين،
because they hate a lot of things, which leads to negative outcomes,
لأنهم يكرهون الكثير من الأشياء، الشيء الذي يقودُ إلى نتائج سلبية،
like racism, violence and Ted Nugent.
مثل العنصرية والعنف وتيد نوغنت المغني والموسيقى والناشط السياسي الأمريكي.
This is not an exhaustive list;
هذه ليست قائمة حصرية،
I'm probably missing 3-7 items.
ربما فاتني 3 إلى 7 بنود.
But the point is,
لكن الهدف هو،
we have to reckon with the haters.
علينا أن نحسب حساب الحاقدين.
But there's variance within this group
لكن هناك اختلاف ضمن هذه المجموعة
and it's not efficient to go after all of them, right?
وليس فعالاً أن نقتفي أثرهم جميعاً، أليس كذلك؟
So what I've done is created a highly scientific Taxonomy of Haters.
لذا ما قمتُ به هو أنني أنشأتُ تصنيفاً علمياً رفيعاً للحاقدين.
I basically took all of the haters,
أخذتُ أساساً جميع الحاقدين،
I put them in a petri dish, like a scientist,
ووضعتهم في طبق مخبري مثل العالِم،
and this is what I found.
وهذا ما وجدته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
First off, we have the trolls.
أولاً، لدينا المتصيدون.
These are your garden-variety digital haters.
هؤلاء هم حديقتكم الرقمية المتنوعة من الحاقدين.
They're the people who quit their jobs
إنهم الأشخاص الذين تركوا وظائفهم
so they can post on YouTube videos all day long.
لذا يمكنهم نشر فيديوهات على يوتيوب طول اليوم.
There's also the drive-by haters.
وهناك أيضاً المدفوعون من قبل الحاقدين.
Now, these people will be at a stoplight,
حالياً، ستسلط الأضواء على هؤلاء الناس،
they'll wait for the light to turn green
سينتظرون تحول الضوء إلى اللون الأخضر
and when it does, they yell, "Go back to your own country!"
وعندما يتحول، سيهتفون بصوتٍ عالٍ، "عودوا إلى أوطانكم!"
Now back in the day, they would've actually gotten out of their cars
الآن مرة في اليوم، سيخرجون فعلياً من سياراتهم
and hated you to your face.
ويحقدون عليكم في وجوهكم.
But they just don't make them like they used to --
ولكن سيفعلوها ليس كما اعتادوا -
which is another sign of the decline in America.
التي هي إشارة أخرى للرفض في أمريكا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The next category
الفئة الثانية
is the mission-oriented-bigot- whose-group-affiliation-
رسالتها الموجهة التعصب ومجموعتها المنتمية
gives-them-cover-for-hating hater.
تعطيها غطاءاً لكره الحاقد.
These guys like to hate via a seemingly nice organization,
يرغبُ هؤلاء الأشخاص في الحقد عبر منظمة تبدو لطيفة،
like a church or a nonprofit,
مثل كنسية أو منظمة غير ربحية،
and they oftentimes like to speak in an old-timey voice.
وغالباً ما يحلو لهم التحدث بصوتٍ عفى عليه الزمن.
But the group I'm most interested in is the swing hater.
لكن ما يثير إهتمامي أكثر هي المجموعة الحاقدة المتقلبة.
The swing hater is sister to the swing voter --
الحاقد المتقلب هو شقيق الناخب المتقلب --
they just can't decide!
لا يستطيعون إتخاذ قرار!
They're like ideological sluts
إنهم مثل الفاسقات صاحبات الفكر
who move from hating to not hating.
الذين يتحولون من الحقد إلى عدم الحقد.
And they do it because they don't have enough information.
ويفعلون ذلك لأنه ليس لديهم معلومات كافية.
This is the group I like to target with social justice comedy.
هذه هي المجموعة التي أرغبُ في استهدافها بكوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية
Why comedy?
لماذا الكوميديا الهزلية؟
Because on a scale of comedy to brochure,
لأنه وعلى مقياس الكوميديا إلى المكتوب في كتيب،
the average American prefers comedy, as you can see from this graph.
يفضّلُ الأمريكي العادي الكوميديا، كما ترون في هذا الرسم البياني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Comedy is very popular.
تحظى الكوميديا بشعبية كبيرة.
And by the way,
وبالمناسبة،
this is a mathematically accurate graph,
هذا رسم بياني دقيق حسابياً،
generated from fake numbers.
نتج عن أرقام وهمية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, the question is:
السؤال حالياً هو:
Why does social justice comedy work?
لماذا تعمل كوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية؟
Because, first off, it makes you laugh.
أولاً بسبب أنها تجعلكم تضحكون.
And when you're laughing, you enter into a state of openness.
وعندما تضحكون، تدخلون في حالة من الصراحة.
And in that moment of openness,
وفي لحظة الصراحة والإنفتاح،
a good social justice comedian can stick in a whole bunch of information,
يمكنُ لممثل كوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية الجيد أن يدفع بباقة كاملة من المعلومات،
and if they're really skilled,
وإذا ما كانوا مهرة حقاً،
a rectal exam.
الفحص الشرجي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here are some ground rules for social justice comedy:
إليكم بعض القواعد الأساسية لكوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية:
first off, it's not partisan.
أولاً، أنها ليست متحيزة
This isn't political comedy, this is about justice,
ليست هذه كوميديا سياسية، إنها حول العدالة،
and no one is against justice.
ولا أحد ضد العدالة.
Two, it's inviting and warm,
ثانياً، أنها جذابة وودية،
it makes you feel like you're sitting inside of a burrito.
تجعلكم تشعرون وكأنكم تجلسون داخل فطيرة بوريتو.
Three, it's funny but sneaky,
ثالثاً، إنها مضحكة، لكنها عابرة،
like you could be hearing an interesting treatise
يمكنكم مثلاً سماع أطروحة مثيرة للإهتمام
on income inequality,
حول تفاوت المداخيل.
that's encased in a really sophisticated poop joke.
مغلفة في شكل نكتة خرائية راقية حقاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here's how I see social justice comedy working.
هكذا أرى عمل كوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية.
A few years ago, I rounded up a bunch of Muslim-American comedians --
قبل عدة سنوات، جمعتُ مجموعة من الممثلين الهزليين الأمريكيين المسلمين
in a non-violent way --
بطريقة سلمية --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And we went around the country
وتجولنا في جميع أنحاء البلاد
to places like Alabama, Arizona, Tennessee, Georgia --
إلى أماكن مثل ألاباما وأريزونا وتينسي وجورجيا --
places where they love the Muzzies --
أماكن حيث يحبون المسلمين
and we did stand-up shows.
وقمنا بعمل عروض ارتجالية.
We called the tour "The Muslims Are Coming!"
أسمينا الجولة "المسلمون قادمون!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We turned this into a movie,
وحولنا هذا إلى فيلم،
and then after the movie came out,
وبعد أن عرض الفيلم،
a known hate group spent 300,000 dollars
أنفقت مجموعة حاقدة معروفة 300000 دولار
on an anti-Muslim poster campaign
على ملصق لحملة معادية للمسلمين
with the MTA -- that's the New York City subway system.
مع هيئة النقل الحضري، وهو نظام مترو الأنفاق في نيويورك.
Now, the posters were truly offensive,
حالياً، كانت الملصقات هجومية حقاً،
not to mentioned poorly designed --
ناهيكم عن سوء تصميمها --
I mean, if you're going to be bigoted,
أعني إذا كنتم تريدون أن تكونوا متعصبين،
you might as well use a better font.
قد تحتاجون أيضاً إلى خط أفضل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But we decided, why not launch our own poster campaign
لكن قررنا، لماذا لا نُطلق ملصق حملتنا الخاصة
that says nice things about Muslims,
التي تقول أشياء لطيفة عن المسلمين،
while promoting the movie.
وفي الوقت نفسه نروج للفليم.
So myself and fellow comedian Dean Obeidallah
لذلك بصحبة زميلي الفنان الكوميدي دين عبيد الله
decided to launch the fighting-bigotry- with-delightful-posters campaign.
قررنا إطلاق حملة ملصقات مبهجة تحارب التعصب.
We raised the money, worked with the MTA for over 5 months,
جمعنا المال وعملنا مع هيئة النقل في منطقة نيويورك لأكثر من خمسة شهور
got the posters approved,
حصلنا على موافقة الملصقات،
and two days after they were supposed to go up,
وبعد يومين حيث كان من المفترض أن تعلَّقْ،
the MTA decided to ban the posters,
قررت هيئة النقل الحضري منع الملصقات،
citing political content.
التي تنقل محتوى سياسي.
Let's take a look at a couple of those posters.
دعونا نلقي نظرة إلى إثنين من هذه الملصقات.
Here's one.
إليكم إحداها.
Facts about Muslims:
حقائق حول المسلمين:
Muslims invented the concept of a hospital.
اخترع المسلمون مفهوم المستشفى.
OK.
حسناً.
Fact: Grown-up Muslims can do more push-ups than baby Muslims.
حقيقة: يمكنُ لكبار المسلمين القيام بالمزيد من تمارين الضغط أكثر من أطفالهم.
Fact: Muslims invented Justin Timberlake.
حقيقة: إخترع المسلمون جاستين تمبيرلك المغني الأمريكي المشهور
Let's take a look at another one.
دعونا ننظر إلى واحدة أخرى.
The ugly truth about Muslims:
الحقيقة البشعة عن المسلمين:
they have great frittata recipes.
لديهم وصفات فريتاتا (عجة بالبيض) رائعة.
Now clearly, frittatas are considered political by the MTA.
من الواضح الآن، أعتبرت العجة محتوى سياسي من قبل هيئة النقل في منطقة نيويورك.
Either that, or the mere mention of Muslims in a positive light
إما ذلك أو مجرد ذكر المسلمين في ضوء إيجابي
was considered political -- but it isn't.
أعتبر سياسياُ -- لكن الأمر ليس كذلك.
It's about justice.
إنها حول العدالة.
So we decided to change
لذلك قررنا أن نغير
our fighting-bigortry- with-delightful-posters campaign
حملة ملصقاتنا المبهجة المعادية للتعصب
and turn it into the fighting-bigotry- with-a-delightful-lawsuit campaign.
وتحويلها إلى حملة دعوى قضائية مبهجة معادية للتعصب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So basically, what I'm saying is a couple of dirt-bag comedians
لذلك أساساً، ما أقوله هو أن بضعة من الممثلين الهزلين المشاكسين
took on a major New York City agency
تحدوا وكالة مدينة نيويورك الرئيسية
and the comedians won.
وفاز الفنانون الهزليون.
(Applause and cheers)
(تصفيق وهتاف)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
Victory was a very weird feeling.
كان الفوز شعوراً غريباً جداً.
I was like, "Is this what blonde girls feel like all the time?
كنتُ مثل، "هل هذا هو شعور الفتيات الشقراوات طول الوقت؟
'Cause this is amazing!"
لأن هذا أمر مذهل!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here's another example.
إليكم مثالاً آخر.
I'm asked everywhere I go: "Why don't Muslims denounce terrorism?"
أُسْأَل في كل مكان أذهب إليه: "لماذا لا يدينُ المسلمون الإرهاب؟"
We do. But OK, I'll take the bait.
إننا نفعل ذلك. لكن حسناً، سآخذُ الطُعم.
So I decided to launch thedailydenouncer.com.
لذلك قررتُ إطلاق الموقع الإلكتروني thedailydenouncer.com
It's a website that denounces terrorism every day of the week,
إنه الموقع الإلكتروني الذي ينددُ بالإرهاب في كل أيام الأسبوع،
while taking the weekends off.
بينما يتوقف في عطلة نهاية الأسبوع.
Let's take a look at an example.
دعونا ننظر إلى أحد الأمثلة.
They generally appear as single-panel cartoons,
تظهر عامةً كلوحة رسوم متحركة منفردة،
"I denounce terrorism! I also denounce people who never fill the paper tray!"
"أنا أشجبُ الأرهاب! وأشجبُ أيضاً هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين لا يملؤون أبداً درج الورق!"
while recognizing that it's ridiculous
والإعتراف بأن ذلك أمرٌ مثير للسخرية
that we have to constantly denounce terrorism.
أنه علينا بإستمرار شجب الإرهاب.
But if bigotry isn't your thing,
لكن إن لم يكن التعصب شيئاً يخصك،
social justice comedy is useful for all sorts of issues.
فكوميديا العدالة الإجتماعية مفيدة لشتى أصناف القضايا.
For example, myself and fellow comedian Lee Camp
على سبيل المثال، زميلي الفنان الكوميدي لي كامب وأنا
went to the Cayman Islands to investigate offshore banking.
ذهبنا إلى جزيرة كايمان لتقصي الحقائق حول حسابات بنكية في الخارج.
Now, the United States loses something like 300 billion dollars a year
حالياً، تخسرُ الولايات المتحدة شيء من قبيل 300،000 مليار دولار سنوياً
in these offshore tax havens.
في ملاذات التهرب من دفع الضرائب.
Not to brag,
ليس للتباهي.
but at the end of every month,
لكن في نهاية كل شهر،
I have something like 5-15 dollars in disposable income.
لدي شيء مثل 5 إلى 10 دولار كدخل مُتاح.
So we walked into these banks in the Cayman Islands
لذلك ذهبنا إلى هذه البنوك في جزيرة كايمان
and asked if we could open up a bank account
وسألنا إذا كان في إستطاعتنا فتح حساب بنكي
with eight dollars and 27 cents.
بمبلغ 8 دولارات و 27 سنتاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The bank managers would indulge us for 30-45 seconds before calling security.
أمهلنا مدراء البنك 30 إلى 45 ثانية قبل إستدعاء الأمن.
Security would come out, brandish their weapons,
سيحضر رجال الأمن ملوحين بأسلحتهم.
and then we would squeal with fear and run away,
ومن ثم سنصرخُ خوفاً ونهرب.
because -- and this is the last rule of social justice comedy --
بسبب -- وهذه هي القاعدة الأخيرة لكوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية --
sometimes it makes you want to take a dump in your pants.
تجعلكم أحياناً ترغبون في التبرز في بناطيلكم.
Most of my work is meant to be fun.
المقصود من معظم أعمالي أن تكون مضحكة.
It's meant to generate a connection and laughter.
تهدفُ إلى توليد التواصل والضحك.
But yes, sometimes I get run off the grounds by security.
لكن نعم، يحصل أحياناً أن أسحب أرضاً من قبل الأمن.
Sometimes I get mean tweets and hate mail.
ويصلني أحياناً تغريدات حاقدة ورسائل كراهية.
Sometimes I get voice mails saying that if I continue telling my jokes,
وأتلقى أحياناً رسائل صوتية تقول إذا واصلتُ أداء نكاتي،
they'll kill me and they'll kill my family.
سيقدمون على قتلي وقتل عائلتي.
And those death threats are definitely not funny.
وهذه التهديدات بالقتل هي بالتأكيد ليست بالشيء المضحك.
But despite the occasional danger,
لكن على الرغم من الخطر في بعض الأحيان،
I still think that social justice comedy is one of our best weapons.
ما زلتُ أعتقد أن كوميديا العدالة الاجتماعية هي واحدة من أفضل أسلحتنا.
I mean, we've tried a lot of approaches to social justice,
أقصدُ أننا حاولنا الكثير من الوسائل للعدالة الاجتماعية،
like war and competitive ice dancing.
مثل الحرب والرقص التنافسي على الجليد.
But still, a lot of things are still kind of awful.
لكن ما تزال الكثير من الأشياء مخيفة نوعاً ما.
So I think it's time we try and tell a really good poop joke.
لذلك أعتقد أنه حان الوقت كي نجرب ونقول طرفة خرائية جيدة حقاً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)